<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A petition for the vindication of the publique use of the Book of Common-Prayer, from some foul, but undeserved aspersions lately cast upon it And for the asserting of the publique use of set-forms of prayer, and dispensing the holy Sacraments. Occasioned by the late ordinance for the ejecting of scandalous, ignorant, and insufficient ministers and school-masters. As also thirty seven quæres concerning the said ordinance, and the particulars thereof. Humbly presented to the most Honourable and highest court of Parliament, now convened at Westminster, anno 1654. With a true account rendred in an epistle prefixed, and an appendix subjoyned, both of the printing and presenting the same. By Lionel Gatford, batchelour in Divinity.</title>
            <author>Gatford, Lionel, d. 1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85836</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G336</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E818_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207397</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899520</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899520</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153957</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85836)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153957)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2391:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A petition for the vindication of the publique use of the Book of Common-Prayer, from some foul, but undeserved aspersions lately cast upon it And for the asserting of the publique use of set-forms of prayer, and dispensing the holy Sacraments. Occasioned by the late ordinance for the ejecting of scandalous, ignorant, and insufficient ministers and school-masters. As also thirty seven quæres concerning the said ordinance, and the particulars thereof. Humbly presented to the most Honourable and highest court of Parliament, now convened at Westminster, anno 1654. With a true account rendred in an epistle prefixed, and an appendix subjoyned, both of the printing and presenting the same. By Lionel Gatford, batchelour in Divinity.</title>
                  <author>Gatford, Lionel, d. 1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 31-62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for John Williams, at the Crown in Saint Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655. [i.e. 1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "December 8"; the second 5 in imprint date has been crossed out and date altered to 1654.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Book of common prayer --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sacraments --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153957:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PETITION For the Vindication of the Publique uſe of the Book of <hi>COMMON-PRAYER,</hi> From ſome foul, but undeſerved aſperſions lately caſt upon it. And for the aſſerting of the Publique uſe of <hi>Set-Forms</hi> of <hi>PRAYER,</hi> and diſpenſing the holy <hi>SACRAMENTS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Occaſioned by the late Ordinance for the ejecting of ſcandalous, ignorant, and inſufficient Miniſters and School-Maſters.</p>
            <p>As alſo thirty ſeven Quaeres concerning the ſaid Ordinance, and the particulars thereof.</p>
            <p>Humbly preſented to the moſt Honourable and Higheſt Court of <hi>PARLIAMENT,</hi> now convened at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Anno <hi>1654.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH A true Account rendred in an <hi>Epiſtle</hi> prefixed, and an <hi>Appendix</hi> ſubjoyned, both of the Printing and Preſenting the ſame.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Lionel Gatford,</hi> Batchelour in Divinity.</p>
            <p>2 CHR<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. 13. v. 9. DEUT. 33. v. 8.10, 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Williams,</hi> at the <hi>Crown</hi> in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:153957:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153957:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HONOURABLE and Higheſt Court of <hi>PARLIAMENT,</hi> now aſſembled at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Lionel Gatford,</hi> Batchelour in Divinity, wiſheth all Wiſdome, Courage, and Fear of the Lord, with all other graces neceſſary for this life, and all comforts and joyes reſerved for a better.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Honourable, and truly honoured,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E pleaſed (<hi>I</hi> moſt humbly beſeech you) to receive by the hands of another, what my preſent infirmities of body, and poverty of condition, will not permit me to preſent unto your Honours by mine own. The following Petition, and certain Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res annexed thereto; both occaſioned by the late Ordinance for the ejecting of ſcandalous, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and inſufficient Miniſters and School-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. An Ordinance deſerving your ſtricteſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, as being ſuggeſted to his Highneſſe by ſome grand, but cloſe underminers of the Proteſtant Religion, for the utter extirpation of the Miniſtery thereof out of this Nation, and
<pb facs="tcp:153957:3"/>therefore already taken (as I am informed) into your moſt pious conſideration, as a work moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming you and your known zeal and affection to the ſaid Religion. And if the ſaid Petition, and Quaers may contribute ought, though never ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to that great and glorious work, I ſhall give God all the glory of it; as I ſhall never ceaſe to ſupplicate him for his aſſiſting you therein, and crowning your endeavours with an happy and honourable ſucceſſe. I have cauſed both the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Quaeres to be Printed, and taken the beſt order I could, at this diſtance with the Stationer, to whoſe care I committed the Printing of them, that your Honours might have each of you a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Copy, to the intent that you might by your ſelves in your retirements, as well as joyntly in your Aſſembly (if you ſee cauſe) peruſe and ſcan every part and clauſe thereof. And if after ſuch a peruſal, your Honours ſhall finde (as I truſt you will) nothing therein either repugnant or prejudicial to truth, and the zealous and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential propugning thereof, or unbeſeeming the propugner, or unworthy of your Honours appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for; I humbly begge your further recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending them (if you ſhall think fit to a more publique view, either of his Highneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:153957:3"/>any other, with what advantage your better Judgements, and more inflamed zeal to Gods glory, and the true Reformed Religion ſhall prompt you to. But if they obtain no other favor but the being read by you, I ſhall repute it no ſmall recompence, as well as honour to have ſuch witneſſes of my being really ſtudious, and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dially deſirous to defend and maintain, to the utmoſt of my weak power and ability, the ſaid true Reformed Proteſtant Religion establiſhed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> againſt all the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and oppugners thereof; as alſo againſt what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſcandalls, reproaches, or aſperſions they can caſt on it. And that as readily and willingly now in theſe times of frenzy and madneſſe on the one hand, as heretofore in thoſe of imprudence and incogitancy on the other. And perhaps the known adverſaries of our Religion (whoſe heads have been and ſtill are very buſie in all the deſigns and contrivances againſt it, though they have and doe make uſe of others hands to act by) may loſe a great part of their preſent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, if they be not wholly fruſtrated, by this ſingle appearance of one poor ſtripling of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> it being known to them and to the world, that (notwithſtanding the fall
<pb facs="tcp:153957:4"/>of ſo many thouſand able and eminent profeſſors and repugners of the ſame Religion, by their Jeſuitical treacheries and conſpiracies) there are yet whole Armies left of the ſame faith and courag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, though they have not ſo publiquely dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ared themſelves, nor indeed might without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>curring ſome cenſure, which they are deſirous to avoid. Howſoever, if that ſtripling be but encouraged with your approbation (as he hath reaſon from former mercies and deliverances to hope for Gods aſſiſtance) he ſhall willingly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard himſelf in the defence of his Religion; and, upon reaſonable warning, will be ready with his Shepherds Scrip, and Paſtoral Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, (though he be ſequeſtred from his flock) to encounter with any Philiſtine, to whom your Honours ſhall ſend or call forth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt devoted ſervant</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="petition">
                  <pb facs="tcp:153957:4"/>
                  <head>TO THE MOST HONOURABLE and Higheſt Court of <hi>PARLIAMENT,</hi> Now Convened at <hi>Weſtminster,</hi> for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of <hi>Lionel Gatford,</hi> B.D.</head>
                  <opener>Moſt humbly ſheweth,</opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat whereas it pleaſed his Highneſs, the Lord Protector, (upon the ſubtil and malicious ſuggeſtions of cloſe, pernicious enemies to the true Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Proteſtant Religion, as your Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in honour of his Highneſſe and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil is bound to conceive) by his Letters to the Judge of the Aſſiſes the laſt <hi>Spring,</hi> to require the Juſtices of Peace to be more particularly carefull of the ſuppreſſing of Ale-houſes and the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer;</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:153957:5"/>And again ſince that, by an Ordinance inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>An O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dinance for the ejecting of Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gnorant, and inſufficient Ministers, &amp;c.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> conjoin the publique and frequent read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or uſing the ſaid Book, with the horrid crimes of holding or maintaining blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and Atheiſtical opinions, of being guilty of Curſing, Swearing, Perjury, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ornation of Perjury, Adultery, Fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Drunkenneſſe, and other abominable crimes mentioned in the ſaid Ordinance; As alſo thereby to adjudge the ſo reading the ſaid Book to be a crime ſo ſcandalous, as that he, that ſhould be guilty thereof, (how thoroughly Orthodox or faithfully labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, how devoutly pious, and eminently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious ſoever he otherwiſe be) ſhould be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected and diſplaced from his Cure of Souls, Benefice, or other place or charge, to his own and poor wife and childrens ruine, if not to the extreme dammage or hazzard of thoſe Souls committed to his Charge, and acknowledged to have been much benefited by his Miniſtery.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Your humble Petitioner, in his zeal to Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the honour of the true Reformed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant
<pb facs="tcp:153957:5"/>Religion (of both which, the ſaid Book hath been inſtrumentally none of the leaſt promoter and advancer) moſt humbly craveth leave to offer theſe few particulars to your moſt ſerious and pious conſideration.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, Whether the joining of the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and Ale-houſes in their ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing, and the reputing and accounting the publique reading or uſing it amongſt ſuch horrid crimes before mentioned, and the adjudging him that ſo readeth or uſeth it, to be therefore ſo ſcandalous, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be ejected out of his Cure or Charge, be not (to ſay the leaſt of it) very injurious and prejudicial to the true Reformed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion it ſelf, and highly diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable both to it and to the true Profeſſors thereof, as alſo much advantagious to the enemies of both, as well in their now more then ordinarily endeavoured, and more then wontedly prevailing ſeducements and temptations, for the perverting and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting many weak brethren, as otherwiſe, when it cannot be denyed, but that the ſaid Book was at firſt compoſed by moſt pious, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, as well as Learned and Orthodox
<pb facs="tcp:153957:6"/>men, eminent for their wiſdome and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in aſſiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing the Reformation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d renowned for their fidelity and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>tancy in ſealing their profeſſion with their bloud: And hath been ſince reviſed, and farther approved and eſtabliſhed by all our pious Proteſtant Princes, with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and conſent of their moſt Judicious and Religious Parliaments; And contains in it the form and matter of the publique wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God by Prayer, and the form and manner of the publique diſpenſing the holy Sacraments, and other neceſſary publique obſervances, conſtantly practiſed and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the Proteſtants here in <hi>England,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince the Reformation, and no ways re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant in any eſſential part thereof to the publique form of Prayer, and Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacraments, uſed in other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches: So that, if that way and manner of the publique worſhip of God by Prayer, and of the publique diſpenſing or adminiſtring the Sacraments, which hath bin the only conſtant and approved way here in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> be ſuch as deſerves not onely utterly to be aboliſhed and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed,
<pb facs="tcp:153957:6"/>but to be joined in the aboliſhing and ſuppreſſing it, with thoſe ſinks of ſin, and nurſeries of vice, common Ale-houſes, and to have the uſing that way and manner reputed amongſt ſuch horrid crimes as by the ſaid Ordinance 'tis reputed, and to be adjudged ſo ſcandalous, as that they who uſe it ought to be deemed and cenſured as unfit &amp; unworthy to officiate in the Church; and for that cauſe alone to be ejected and diſplaced: It will thereupon eaſily be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred and concluded, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> (the acknowledged Bulwark and Fortreſſe, as well as aſyle and refuge of all the Proteſtants in Chriſtendome) hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto foully and groſly, yea, criminouſly and ſcandalouſly erred in two main Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals of Religion, and diſcriminating notes of a true Church, <hi>viz.</hi> the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of God, and the right and lawful adminiſtration of the Sacraments. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the granting or ſuppoſing this, be not very injurious and prejudicial to the true Reformed Proteſtant Religion it ſelf, and highly diſhonourable both to it and to the true Profeſſors thereof, &amp;c. as is before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged,
<pb facs="tcp:153957:7"/>is humbly ſubmitted to your Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, for the vindicating of the true Reformed Proteſtant Religion, and the profeſſors thereof, from this foul, but moſt unjuſt ſcandal and aſperſion, and from the injury, prejudice and dammage, that it and they may ſuffer thereby; Your humble Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner further prayeth, that his Highneſſe the Lord Protector, may be ſo fairly and obſervantly treated with, and adviſed by your Honours, his now greateſt Council, concerning that particular, that without the leaſt reflection of diminution upon his Honour and Wiſdome, (ſo far as is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) his own opinion, or rather ſudden conception upon others ſuggeſtions, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> may bee taken off, &amp; changed into better thoughts; and ſo the honour of that Book (ſo far at leaſt, as concerns the honour of God, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and the true Reformed Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion) be preſerved, which is no more then the Apoſtles themſelves did in the aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Jewiſh Rites and Ceremonies, how inconſiſtent ſoever with the Chriſtian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,
<pb facs="tcp:153957:7"/>and practiſe, and may much more be indulged to the reverend and religious worſhip of many thouſands and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands eminently renowned Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>And for the ſame ends, your Petitioner in the third place, offereth to your Honors this humble motion and earneſt ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That you would be pleaſed (with the conſent of his Highneſſe firſt obtained) to publiſh a decree or command, That all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of what religion or profeſſion ſoever, that have ought to object or except againſt ſet forms of publique Prayer, and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments in general, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, do (by ſome few of their own religion and profeſſion, choſen by them for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for the avoidng of tumults and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) within ſuch a time give in to your Honours, either written or printed, all or the chief of the reaſons &amp; grounds of thoſe their objections and exceptions. And that your Petitioner, (though very weak and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to appear in ſo great a cauſe) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſome few other of thoſe many that are of his judgement, may, upon ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb facs="tcp:153957:8"/>notice thereof given to them, and ſome ſmall charges, by reaſon of his and their known poverty, allowed them, be admitted to return anſwer to thoſe objections and exceptions; and then have ſome further time aſſigned them to clear and make good to his Highneſſe and to your Honours, theſe three Aſſertions.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. That Set Forms of publique Prayer, and diſpenſing of the Saeraments, are more agreeable to and conſiſtent with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and rules of Prayer, and diſpenſing the Sacraments contained in ſacred Scripture, then <hi>ex tempore</hi> Prayers and Arbitrary modes of diſpenſing theſe Ordinances are.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. That it is requiſite and neceſſary for every ſettled Church in every Nation to have (as anciently and lately they had) known Set-Forms both of publique Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and of publique diſpenſation of the Sacraments, that ſo errors in both may be the better avoided, and the uncharitable judging of each other prevented, and peace and truth preſerved.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. That the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and adminiſtration of the Sacraments for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
<pb facs="tcp:153957:8"/>eſtabliſhed and uſed here in <hi>England,</hi> is abſolutely the beſt Form and freeſt from all juſt exceptions in all eſſentiall points and practiſes of Religion, that ever yet ſaw light in the Chriſtian world, and none of the weakeſt Forts, that the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> had againſt Popery, and other errors, and hereſies. And therefore may by your Honours mediation to his Highneſſe, and with his and your joint approbation and confirmation, be ſtill continued in this Church (at leaſt in thoſe Congregations that ſhall accept and deſire it) without the ſcandal of any, or prejudice to thoſe that ſhall uſe it.</p>
                  <closer>And for this your juſtice, and zeal for the honour of God, and the true Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Proteſtant Religion, your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner with many thouſands ſhall faithfully and devoutly pray, &amp;c.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:153957:9"/>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:153957:9"/>
                  <head>CERTAIN QUAERIES Concerning the <hi>Ordinance</hi> for ejecting of Scandalous, Ignorant, and Inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Schoolmaſters.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">Humbly preſented to the Higheſt Court of PARLIAMENT now conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at <hi>Weſtminster.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <byline>By L.G. B.D.</byline>
                  <div n="1" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 1.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether the Ordinance it ſelf be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the known Lawes, and other juſt claims of the Subjects of this Nation,) as <hi>Magna Charta</hi> and the Petition of Right) for the preſervation of themſelves, their rights, and proprieties: For that by them (as we are informed) no Subject ought or can be ejected out of his poſſeſſion or lively-hood, unleſſe ſuch an ejection, or diſpoſſeſsion be firſt legally procured by vertue
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153957:10"/>and power of ſome eſtabliſhed Law or Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, conſtituted and conſented unto by the Supreme Governour, and the repreſentative of the Subjects, the Parliament.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 2.</head>
                     <p>Whether, if an Ordinance made by the Protector and his Councill, for the ejecting of Miniſters out of their Livings and and lively-hoods, be owned ſince ſubmitted unto, as authority ſufficient for the ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, The late King and his Councill be not thereby ſuperabundantly juſtified againſt all thoſe late Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of the pretended illegallities of their Acts, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees or orders made by them at the Council board, in far inferiour caſes to this of poſſeſsion and lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and inſtanced in by the late Parliament, as grand grievances of the Subjects, and an introduction of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary power, at leaſt an endeavouring to bring <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter Hall</hi> to <hi>Whitehall.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 3.</head>
                     <p>Whether by the ſame authority, an Ordinance may not be made, for the ejecting or ſequeſtring of any other Subjects of England, (even the Commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, authorized by this Ordinance themſelves, as well as any) that ſhall, by other Commiſsioners no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated for that purpoſe, be found guilty of ſome of the ſame, or of any other crimes, that by ſuch an Ordinance ſhall be reputed crimes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 4.</head>
                     <p>Whether the ſame Powers that made this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, when they have judged ſuch and ſuch crimes in Miniſters to deſerve the ejection of thoſe that are
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153957:10"/>guilty of them out of their Lively-hoods, ought not in equity and conſcience as in a true ſincere deteſtation of thoſe ſinnes, in whomſoever they finde them, to conſtitute and appoint alſo ſome Commiſsioners in each County to cenſure ſeverely and puniſh ſharply all the ſame, much more far greater crimes in others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Miniſters. For ſurely, though the ſame crimes be greater, when found in Miniſters, then in others: yet ſinnes of that high nature, as to deſerve to be puniſhed with no leſſe then ejection, when found in Miniſters, cannot but be ſo great in themſelves, as to deſerve ſome proportionable puniſhment, when they are found in others, eſpecially in magiſtrates, and men of place and authority.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 5.</head>
                     <p>Whether the Lord Protector's Succeſſour may not with as much equity make another Ordinance for the ejecting of all thoſe, both Clergy and Lay-men, out of their eſtates and livelyhoods, who have been active in this Commiſsion of ejecting Miniſters, or otherwiſe guilty of any other crimes, which ſhall by him and his Councill be judged crimes and worthy of ejection? And whether this preſent Ordinance may not prove an unhappy preſident to that purpoſe, not to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or whiſpered againſt by any that ſubmits to this.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 6.</head>
                     <p>Whether his Highneſſe, by imparting ſo much power to any five Commiſſioners in every County, as is by this Ordinance imparted, without admitting of any appeal from their Judgement either to himſelf, or to his Council, or to his Judges of Aſsiſes, or to any
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:153957:11"/>of his Courts in Weſtminſter, may not thereby, ere he is aware have all or the moſt of the Livings and Cures in in every County, voyded and emptied of ſuch Miniſters, as are at the leaſt contented to ſubmit to his Government, and to live quietly and patiently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, without attempting ought againſt him or it, And inſtead of ſuch, to have them filled again with ſuch Pro-miniſters, as will neither be contented with his government, nor with any other? And what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents or effects may ſoon follow thereupon in this factious and divided Nation, wherein (beſides Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itick Papiſts, who are enemies to all Governours, but thoſe of their own leaven) ſuch multitudes of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, Quakers, and other Hereticks, that are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to all Government, are lately crept up to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ſtrength, may be too ſoon felt, and to late thought on. His Highneſſe cannot but remember, what a dangerous deſigne it was not long ſince thought by wiſe men, for ſome Commiſsioners to have power to buy in Impropriations, and to recommend Miniſters to them, or to inlarge their Livings by them, (though admitted by Biſhops) only, for that it was conceived that thoſe Commiſſioners would thereby obliege the Miniſters in ſuch cures too much to them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 7.</head>
                     <p>Whether in all penall Acts or Ordinances for the puniſhment of any Crimes or offences, it hath not been the conſtant practice of the Law-givers of this Nation, and ſo ought in Conſcience ever to be. That no ſuch Act or Ordinance ſhould commence or begin to be of any force, till there had been firſt ſome fair warning
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153957:11"/>given to all the Subjects of the Nation, to beware for the future, after ſuch or ſuch a time, of committing ſuch or ſuch a crime or offence: And for that cauſe, the tenour of ſuch penall Lawes did conſtantly runne in theſe or the like termes. Be it enacted and conſtituted, &amp;c. That if any man ſhall, after ſuch a day in ſuch a year, do thus or thus, then he ſhall ſuffer ſo and ſo: In Gods own account (who hates ſin with an infinite ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, above what any man can do) where there is no Law, there is no tranſgreſsion, for ſin is a tranſgreſsion of the Law, and where there is no tranſgreſsion there ought to be no puniſhment: and although the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Gods Law by any crime or offence, be a fault meriting puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t from that Power, which is ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God to be a revenger to execute wrath upon him that doth evil, yet 'tis worth the queſtioning, whether any ſuch Power may or ought to puniſh any tranſgreſsion of Gods Law with any puniſhment, till he have given the people under his power warning thereof. and then too, 'tis much more diſputable, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he may, by any Law, puniſh any tranſgreſsion of Gods Law with any puniſhment, that God hath not preſcribed in his Law, before he have given them war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſuch a puniſhment, or rather it is not to be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned at all, it being clear that he ought not, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Law of God or man, that can in equity be of any force to puniſh till it be a Law, and therefore may not puniſh for what was done before it had a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a puniſhment, to which it ſelf onely gave the force of being a puniſhment to that offence or tranſgreſsion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="query">
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:153957:12"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 8.</head>
                     <p>Whether the making of an Ordinance by any Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for the puniſhment of crimes committed before that Ordinance was made, and that where no ſuch pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty was ever before by any Law in force inflicted, Be not a rendring of every Subject unſecure in his eſtate, body and life it ſelf, be he never ſo obedient to all Laws, and punctually carefull to obſerve them; When as, for ought any man knowes, that which he did, ſometime ſince, or now doeth, and had then, and hath now, no penalty at all inflicted upon the doing it, or but a light one, may, within a little time after, be reputed and adjudged by the ſupream power a crime worthy of the forfeiture of his eſtate, or the impriſonment or other torture or torment of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or the loſſe of his life it ſelf, and accordingly he may ſuffer either in one or all of them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 9.</head>
                     <p>Whether the Commiſſioners appointed by the Ordinance to hear and determine concerning the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of Miniſters and the charges and accuſations brought againſt them, Be ſuch as in Law and right reaſon ought to be authorized for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, becauſe they are all ſecular or Lay-men; (for the clergy Commiſſioners that are nominated are but Cyphers, and have no power by the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to meddle in any thing, ſave in the inquiring and judging in part who are ignorant and inſufficient.) For although we Miniſters of the Reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church of England do acknowledge our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153957:12"/>ſelves ſubject to the ſecular power, yet we have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, till theſe times of our deep ſufferings, had ſo much Priviledge and immunity granted us by our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Princes and Parliaments, as that we have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pettually had our Eccleſiaſticall Judges to heare and de ermine all, or the moſt Eccleſiaſticall cauſes and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires as weas our temporall judges in all civil. And when wel were judged by temporal Judges, they were ſuch learned and approved prudent and upright men, or at leaſt thought to be ſuch, when they were cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to that weighty and honourable imployment, as that they were intruſted with hearing and determining all matters of Civile Judicature throughout the whole Realme, and leaſt intereſted in thoſe ſeverall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Circui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s wherein they were aſſigned Judges.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, becauſe they are, many of them, ſuch Lay-men, as have abundantly declared themſelves very great diſlikers of, if not enemies to thoſe Clergy men of whom they are made Judges; and ſome of them have given too much occaſion to be reputed Antiminiſters, and ſuch as doe not either love or allow the very office and function of Miniſters.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, becauſe ſome of them, and they of the Beſt rank from whom Miniſters might hope and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to receive the moſt juſtice and legall favour, may be feared to be put into Commiſſion, not ſo much for acting there in themſelves, or to reſtrain and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate others over-activeneſſe and violence, as for the countenancing thoſe other Commiſſioners that are moſt inferiour, and known to be very active and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153957:13"/>violent againſt Miniſters. For that ſome of them are made Commiſſioners, whoſe places and offices re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire their conſtant attendance on his Highneſſe, or nere him in ſome of his Courts at Weſtminſter: And others are made Commiſſioners for ſeverall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in all which t'is impoſſible for them to exerciſe that power, or but very ſeldome. And ſome alſo of thoſe Commiſſioners in ſome Counties, if not in the moſt, will be very unwilling to act in ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, being yoaked with ſuch inferiour and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe generally diſtaſted coaſſeſſors, as they know ſome of them to be. And ſo for theſe and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſons, the whole power and authority, at leaſt the principall if not the ſole exerciſe thereof, for the ejecting of Miniſters will be devolved into the hands of ſome few in every County, whoſe juſtice and moderation, the beſt of Miniſters have reaſon to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, becauſe too many of ſuch a numerous Synedrion of Commiſſioners may have children, kindred, or friends, whoſe want of a Living, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of a better, may too much byas thoſe Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners in their Judgements, eſpecially againſt ſuch Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters as have good Livings.</p>
                     <p>Fifthly, becauſe divers of thoſe reputed ſcandalous crimes, whereof thoſe Commiſſioners are to judge, are not properly within their Cognizance, nor indeed within the ſphere of many of their underſtandings. As what is curſing and ſwearing, properly ſo termed, and what is not, what is Drunkenneſſe rightly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and what is not; what is a prophanation of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153957:13"/>Lords day, and what is not, what is the true profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Religion and godlineſſe, and what is not, and who are the ſtrict profeſſors thereof and who are not, what it is to ſcoffe at or revile the profeſſion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion or the ſtrict Profeſſors thereof, and what is not, what are ſuch licentious practiſes (beſides Whitſon-Ales, Wakes, Morris Dances, May-poles, and Stage-playes) as do incourage men in a looſe and prophane converſation, and what are not. For often experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence tells us, that ſome account bare aſſertions ſo and ſo framed to be oathes, and others think thoſe that are oathes to be none: ſome repute the drinking more than quencheth thirſt to be drunkenneſſe, (and here in Norfolke hath been already oath made by a man of no inferiour quality, that a Miniſter was drunk, becauſe he ſmelt of drink, and his tongue did falter: by which t'is clear that he neither knew what it is to be drunk, nor what it is to ſwear one ſo to be) and others ſay a man is not drunk, till he be wholly deprived by his exceſſive drinking of his reaſon and underſtanding in the uſe and exerciſe of it: and the moſt learned Judges in the Law have differed very much in their Judgements about it, as well as the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſts in Divinity. And for the prophanation of the Lords Day, Some, and they not a few have accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the dreſſing of any meat, or the doing of any other ordinary work, or the uſing any common talk on that Day, to be a prophanation of the Day: Others, that would not like it well to be thought prophane, have to their power maintained both by their practiſe and otherwiſe, that the working on their trades, or the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153957:14"/>buying and ſelling in publick markets on that Day (eſpecially if it be not in the hour) of publick prayer and preaching) is no prophanation of the Day. But for the ſcoffing at, or reviling the ſtrict profeſſion or profeſſors of Religion or Godlineſſe. There are ſo many ſeverall factions, that claim the profeſſion of Religion and Godlineſſe to themſelves, and to thoſe only of their faction, that the true Reformed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion (which is the moſt ſound, ſincere, true Religion in the world) is by them not vouchſafed the name of Religion, but made the ſcorn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of them and theirs; and the true profeſſors thereof are become the chiefly perſecuted men of the times. So that now, if any zealous Elijah ſhall but uſe any holy Sarcaſme againſt any one of theſe numerous factions, much more reprove any of them for their folly and frenzy, he may be accounted by ſome of his Judges a ſcoffer at, or a reviler of the ſtrict profeſſion, or profeſſors of Religion or Godlineſſe, as we in this County have already a ſufficient example thereof, where a very grave, prudent, conſcientious Miniſter (as he is generally voyced) hath been convented for ſcoffing at the profeſſors of Religion, becauſe he ſpake againſt hypocrites, underſtanding by them (as the witneſſe upon oath ſaid he believed,) the Godly and religious. Then for other licentious practiſes, beſides Whitſon-Ales, Wakes &amp;c. by which men are incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged in a looſe and prophane converſation, They may (for ought is known to the contrary) be exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and interpreted by ſome five Commiſſioners, as comprehending all games, ſports or recreations of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153957:14"/>youth, how innocent ſoever: And that Miniſter that will not joyn with or aſſiſt ſome indiſcreet ignorant Sectaries in their interdicting or diſturbing the youth of his Pariſh, in any ſuch game, ſport, or recreation (though he can or do alledge more reaſons for it, then they or any of their ſect can anſwer) may be judged an incourager or countenancer of men in looſe and prophane converſation.</p>
                     <p>Sixthly, becauſe it is as irregular and improper (if not more) for Lay-men to be Commiſſioners in Eccleſiaſticall cauſes and affairs, as for Clergy-men to be commiſſioners in Civil. And it may, without any derogation to any on the one part, or oſtentation of any on the other, be very well preſumed, that there may be found in every County divers Clergy men every way as fit and able to be Commiſſioners of peace, as many Lay-men named in the Ordinance, are to be Commiſſioners in the preſent Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quar.</hi> 10.</head>
                     <p>Whether the joyning of ſo many Miniſters with the Lay-Commiſſioners, and giving them no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity at all to act, unleſſe it be in declaring and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judging in part, who are ignorant and inſufficient (which is as nothing, ſuch Miniſters being more ſecure then the moſt knowing and able; unleſſe we could imagine, that ſome of the Clergy-Commiſſioners themſelves will be brought to the teſt and tryall) Does not, even by that, as well as by other mediums, apparently diſcover to all ſeeing eyes, that the deſign of thoſe, that firſt ſuggeſted this Ordinance to his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153957:15"/>Highneſſe, is utterly to ruine and extirpate the whole Proteſtant Miniſtry of England, the long laboured deſign of the Jeſuits, but never ſo much to be feared as now. And for the full accompliſhment thereof with the more ſecurity of Miniſters and the leſſe ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of others that love them; they thought it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to have ſo many Miniſters in each County na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Ordinance as Commiſſioners, that ſo it might be preſumed, that ſeing there were ſo many Miniſters in Commiſſion, they would not ſuffer any of their own tribe or calling to be ejected, but ſuch as highly deſerved it, and of whom there ſhould be little or no hope of reclaiming. But then thoſe Miniſters ſo nominated muſt have no power at all allowed them, more then to tickle them, and blinde others, with the empty title of Commiſſioners, (though they had known too many of them to have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive enough formerly in the ruining of others of their Brethren) for fear leaſt ſome even of thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive ones, having ſeen the ſad effect of that their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer activeneſſe, and had ſome remorſe of conſcience for it; (which is my conſtant prayer, that they may have, if they have not) and being thereupon become of more bowels and compaſſion towards the reſt of their Brethren, as well as more ſenſible of their own approaching ruine (for they that perſecute Miniſters, though it be at the firſt by the aſſiſtance of Miniſters, will not willingly leave any Miniſters unperſecuted, no not thoſe, that have ſo aſſiſted them) ſhould now begin to conſider better what they doe; and not conſent or yield, that any Miniſter of any good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153957:15"/>and worth (though unhappily guilty of too many infirmities, as who is not?) ſhould be ejected or diſplaced, and ſo undone and ruined, whom they could deliver from the malice and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of their perſecutors, the perfect haters of all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 11.</head>
                     <p>Whether the carefull joyning of five Commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Laitie, at the leaſt, with five or more Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the Clergy, in the caſe of ignorance, and inſufficiency, (the onely caſe wherein the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of the Clergy, have ought to do) or rather the giving of the five Comiſſioners of the Laitie the chief power in that caſe alſo, and making the Clergie Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners onely their aſsiſtants therein, may not be ſuſpected to have been contrived in favour to thoſe juſtly ignorant, inſufficient Mechanicks and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther illiterate Laicks, that have lately either crept in or been thruſt into ſeverall Livings or cures of Souls, and for the preſerving them from Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ejected for their groſſe ignorance and inſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. For otherwiſe, if whomſoever the Clergy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners, though five, or ten, or more, ſhould judge to be ignorant and inſufficient, ought to be reputed ſo upon their ſo judging, it might have been feared, that the moſt of thoſe Idol Shepherds muſt have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to their old trades again; and many more, that are gaping for other Miniſters Livings, would not adventure the ſo filling their unhallowed mouthes, leaſt an after examination ſhould force them to throw them up again, ere they had well ſwallowed them:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:153957:16"/>And ſo the people of ſuch Pariſhes ſhould murmur and complaine for want of Miniſters, or ſome things inſtead of them. Whereas now, if any ſuch ſhould be judged never ſo ignorant and inſufficient by the Clergy-Commiſsioners, they have not much cauſe to fear, but that their brethren of the Laity, being ſome as ignorant as themſelves, will be more favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to them, and preſerve them from ejection rather then any, as being fitteſt to converſe and comply with them, or to be ſervants and ſlaves to them, without any gainſaying or contradicting whatſoever they ſay or do.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 12.</head>
                     <p>Whether it be not againſt both the Lawes of God and man, that the Oath of one witneſſe with other concurrent evidence of the charge &amp;c. (as is by this Ordinance conſtituted) ſhould be received as a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent teſtimony for the ejecting of a Miniſter out of his Living or Cure of ſouls? whereas an accuſation ought not to be received againſt an Elder, under two or three witneſſes. 1 <hi>Timoth,</hi> 5.19. And one witneſſe is by Gods expreſſe command forbidden to rife up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any man, for any iniquity or for any ſin, or but at the mouth of two witneſſes, or at the mouth of three witneſſes the matter is to be eſtabliſhed. <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.15.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 13.</head>
                     <p>Whether that Law of God recorded, <hi>Deut.</hi> 19. from <hi>ver.</hi> 16. to the end, (namely, That if a falſe witneſſe did riſe up againſt any man to teſtifie againſt him that which is wrong, and the Judges upon inquiſition (which they by that Law were
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:153957:16"/>bound to make) did find that the witneſſe was a falſe witneſſe, and had teſtified falſely againſt his brother; They ſhould then do to him as he had thought to have done unto his brother. And ſo (not otherwiſe) they ſhould put away evill from among them, &amp;c.) cloſe not in the equity of it, if not in the very precept, (as farre as it may poſsibly be obſerved) oblige us Chriſtians to this day: And whether that Law ought not to be more eſpecially obſerved and put in execution in caſe of a falſe witneſſe riſing up againſt a Miniſter; and above all, in this particular caſe; wherein the teſtimony of one witneſſe is to be received againſt a Miniſter, for the ejecting him out of his Living. For if a falſe witneſſe were ſo to be puniſhed, when the teſtimony of one falſe witneſſe could do no man any hurt, unleſs another or two more did conſpire with him in the fame teſtimony much more then now in this caſe, when the teſtimony of one ſuch witneſſe may ruine a man. And if a falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, of what ranck ſoever he were, was to be ſo ſeverely dealt with, when he roſe up againſt any man, though never ſo much inferiour to him, and teſtified falſely aganſt him; though perhaps only that man, againſt whom he ſo teſtified, were injured thereby, or ſome few others; How much more then ſhould the extremity of that puniſhment be inflicted now; when any baſe inferiour fellow may, by riſing up and bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing falſe witneſſe againſt a Miniſter of the Goſpell, ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ruine, not onely that Miniſter, but his whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and do no ſmall wrong to his whole Pariſh or cure of ſouls, and to the ſouls of many others beſides.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="query">
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:153957:17"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 14.</head>
                     <p>Whether, If the teſtimony of any one man, with ſomewhat elſe, which five Commiſsioners ſhall judge to be concurrent evidence, be ſufficient to eject any Miniſter, It may not be evidently and viſibly foreſeen; That now ſuch a door of hope to ruine Miniſters is opened, and ſuch an eaſie way chalked out for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing it, there will ſuddenly be very few mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters left in England to exerciſe their miniſtery; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially conſidering the profeſſed diſtaſte and hatred that hath of late been openly proclaimed and publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſeverall numerous factions, and hereticall and ſchiſmaticall combinations, againſt the ordination, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, office, and ſettled maintainance of Miniſters. As, that all that have been ordained by Biſhops, are Antichriſtian; That the orders and degrees of Miniſters, and the power and authority, that they pretend to have over others of their Brethren the people of God, is a mere uſurpation: That their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and function is needleſſe and ſuperfluous; And, which hath the moſt abettors, That their Tithes and ſettled maintainance, which God and the Lawes have given and confirmed to them, are Jewiſh, Popiſh, and unjuſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quae.</hi> 15.</head>
                     <p>Whether, if ſuch teſtimony, and ſuch concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Evidence, as was inſtanced in by the laſt Quaere, be ſufficient to eject any Miniſter, either a mans own Miniſter, or any other, The moſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, orthodox, laborious, conſcienſcious Miniſters, that are, which do moſt ſtoutly oppoſe Hereticks and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153957:17"/>Schiſmaticks, moſt ſeverely reprove ſin, moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully incite to holineſſe, and moſt religiouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their own lives to their doctrines, be not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (conſidering the Devills and wicked mens malice againſt ſuch) more ſubject to have ſome criminous accuſation or other brought againſt them, then other Miniſters, that are more obnoxious themſelves, but withall leſſe earneſt againſt the vices of others? And ſo whether this Ordinance which is pretended to be conſtituted for the more effectuall propagating the Goſpell and the ſettlement of a painfull Miniſtery in this Nation, will not in probability, prove a grand hinderance of the liberty of the Goſpell, and a ſtrong temptation to the Miniſters thereof, to forbear their crying aloud, and not ſparing to tell the people their ſins and their tranſgreſſions, and to chooſe rather to preach only ſmooth things unto them, that may hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and pleaſe them, And ſo both Miniſters and people to periſh together in their iniquity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 16</head>
                     <p>Whether that clauſe, To proceed to the examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of witneſſes upon Oath (if the cauſe require) as well for and on the behalf of the perſon accuſed &amp;c. as for proof of the ſaid Charge, Articles &amp;c. Does not leave it to five Commiſſioners will and pleaſure, whether they ſhall think it fit to examine any witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, either on the Miniſters, or on the accuſers part, upon oath, or no. And if ſo; whether ſuch an arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, unlimited power and Commiſſion was ever granted by any Chriſtian to be exerciſed over Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or by any ſober Heathen, over Heathen or Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="query">
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:153957:18"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 17.</head>
                     <p>Whether that cloſe couched proviſo, of allowing all neceſſary charges incident to the ejecting, ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring, or removing of Miniſtets, Be not too great an incouragement, as well as temptation, to the enemies and adverſaries of thoſe of that ſacred function, to riſe up againſt them, and to appear either accuſers of them, or witneſſes of ſuch accuſations, how unjuſt ſoever? When our Saviour Chriſt, in ſending forth his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples did forewarn and forearm them, and in them all other diſpenſers of his Goſpell, againſt revilings, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, and falſe accuſations, amongſt other argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that he uſed, he told them, that ſo the world perſecuted the Prophets, ſo that, his Prophets, his Apoſtles, his Miniſters, in all Ages, have been and ſhall be reviled, perſecuted, and falſly accuſed; And needs muſt they be ſo in this age above other, if a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward be allowed them that ſhall do it, and they, who ſhould keep off the Miniſters (as much as in them li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) from being ſo injuriouſly charged, ſhall allow them their Charges, that deal ſo with them. The Miniſters of the Goſpell are ſent forth, as Lambes into the midſt of Wolves: and if thoſe ſhepherds of the people, that ſhould defend thoſe Lambes from ſuch Wolves, ſhall allow ſuch wolves ſome of thoſe Lambes bloods for worrying them; 'tis the infinite mercy and providence of that great Shepherd, that all thoſe his Lambes are not devoured; for 'tis not their ſerpentine wiſdome, nor done like innocency that can protect them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 18.</head>
                     <p>Whether if we conſider the proneneſſe of man in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:153957:18"/>generall both to ſwear and ſwear falſely, when it may either ſatisfy their malice, or otherwiſe conduce to the obtaining their baſe ends; as alſo the great and horrid violation of oaths and covenants, that this our Nation in particular is guilty of; together with the deſperate Atheiſme, and damnable practice of common ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that abounds in all parts thereof; and all theſe added to the other arguments before hinted, It be not much to be feared, That this ordinance for the eject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Miniſters for perjury and ſubordination of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, will, by its admitting of ſuch witneſſes againſt Miniſters, as it admits and incourages, inſtead of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and puniſhing one Miniſter guilty of thoſe abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable crimes, occaſion many hundreds, yea thouſands of other men, whoſe ſouls ought to be more regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, wittingly and frequently to run into thoſe ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtroying abominations? And who ſhall anſwer for them?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 19.</head>
                     <p>Whether, all thoſe things deemed and reputed by this Ordinance to be crimes, and ſuch crimes as are ſo ſcandalous, that every Miniſter, that is guilty thereof, muſt be ejected, be any crimes at all, or ſo much as ſins, or not. As firſt, thoſe often diſputed and diverſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined games of Cards and Dice; provided that they be onely for recreation, and for no wager or ſponſion, or for no other, then what is neither preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall to the looſer in his eſtate, nor detrimentall to any that he is bound to provide for, and that there be no provoking of either gameſter to intemperancy of language or diſturbance of paſſion, Secondly, that long continued, univerſally approved, and often ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:153957:19"/>to uſe of the Common prayer book of which I have elſewhere in my Petition to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, humbly declared my Judgement, and for the vindicating whereof, I ſhall willingly undertake what ſhall be required of me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 20.</head>
                     <p>Whether thoſe crimes which are juſtly ſo reputed, but are already puniſhable by other Laws, or by ſuch Acts, as are for the preſent reputed Laws, with very much ſeverity (as, amongſt other named or referred to by the Ordinance, that crime of Adultery, which is by a late Act to be puniſhed with death, as well in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters as in others) have not a ſufficient puniſhment already ſet or provided for the Committers of them, I before this Ordinance of ejection came forth?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 21.</head>
                     <p>Whether the making Adultery in a Miniſter to be puniſhed with ejection ſhall free him from ſuffering the other puniſhment of death inflicted by a former Act: or muſt a Miniſter be puniſhed with both: or, becauſe the Act for puniſhing Adultery with death was ſo cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telouſly and warily framed with ſuch reſtrictions and proviſo's, as that 'tis a queſtion, whether it will make men more fearfull or more ſecure in the commiting it, by reaſon of the extreme difficulties of proving any guilty of it ſo as that Act requires: As there was good reaſon it ſhould, becauſe it concerned the lives of men, and thoſe eſpecially, men of other rancks and degrees, and of other Callings and Profeſſions, more than Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. And therefore there muſt be ſome other courſe taken for the finding Miniſters guilty of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery with much more caſe and facility; or elſe it
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:153957:19"/>would be in vain to mention that crime. And to that purpoſe it is by this Ordinance conſtituted, That if but one witneſſe, whoſoever he be, will but ſwear that any Miniſter did commit Adultery, and ſomething elſe be produced that five commiſſioners ſhall judge to be concurrent evidence, the poor Miniſter muſt be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted guilty of Adultery and ſo ejected. But then from hence ariſeth another ſmall queſtion, whether ſuch a Miniſter that is ſo judged to be guilty of Adultery, be indeed gnilty or not? For if he be not, why is he eje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted? And if he be, why is his life ſpared? Or why may not the Act take away, what the Ordinance leavs him? And ſo indeed the poor Miniſters themſelves may be ſpeedily provided for, when they are ſo eject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed though their wives and children may ſtarve out a while upon ſome poor pittance, that the Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners ſhall perhaps allow them, though there be no proviſion made for them in caſe of their husbands or fathers deaths.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 22</head>
                     <p>Whether the Committing any one of thoſe crimes, truly ſo adjudged by the Ordinance, ſome years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and after true unfeigned repentance ſince the Committing it, ſo that the Perſon guilty of that crime hath not only the guilt pardoned by God, but Gods promiſe alſo, that it ſhall not be mentioned unto him, Ought notwithſtanding to be puniſhed with ejection of the ſame perſon out of all his Livelyhood.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 23</head>
                     <p>Whether the being guilty of any one or more of theſe crimes be a ground ſufficient to deprive a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of exerciſing his Miniſteriall function and thoſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153957:20"/>abilities which God hath given him, and which he is bound to exerciſe, with no leſſe then a dreadfull woe denounced againſt him, if he do not. And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom ſhall that woe light, if the Miniſter be forcibly debarred or hindred from the exerciſe of them?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 24</head>
                     <p>Whether a Miniſter, guilty of one or more of theſe crimes, may not (notwithſtanding his guiltines there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) do God good ſervice by his preaching and diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Sacrament to thoſe that are willing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous, for all that, to partake of thoſe Ordinances diſpenſed by him. Or whether the virtue and efficacy of thoſe ordinances do ſo depend upon the goodneſſe and badneſſe of the diſpenſers thereof, as to be effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious or not efficacious, according as the diſpenſers are Godly or wicked?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 25.</head>
                     <p>Whether, If a Miniſter be guilty of one or more of thoſe crimes, he ought not firſt to be told thereof, and gently and meekly admoniſhed by ſome or other in private, without diſcovering ſuch a father's naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to others: And if he fall into the ſame Sin or ſins again, then to be admoniſhed thereof before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: And if he then amend not, to be ſeverely cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and chaſtiſed by ſome in publick authority, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he be quite cut off and rejected from the exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his function for ever? And what grounds are there in ſacred writ for ſuch an ejection of Miniſters, as the Ordinance adjudgeth?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 26.</head>
                     <p>Whether there are not in ſome Miniſters other
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:153957:20"/>crimes of as high a nature and as deep guilt, as divers of thoſe named in the Ordinance, and as much, if not more prejudiciall to the Glory of God, and to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of thoſe people that are committed to their charge, that are left unpuniſhed by that Ordinance: As Pride, Covetouſneſſe, malice, falſe-accuſation of brethren, treachery, Apoſtaſie from the truth, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, inſtability of doctrine, being of one opinion one day, and condemning all that are not of the ſame, and deſerting that opinion the next day if the wind turn, the having mens perſons in admiration becauſe of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, the running greedily after the error of Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am for reward, the partaking in the gainſaying of Core, the propheſying or preaching lies, the neglect, if not contempt of Gods ordinances, eſpecially the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, the violation of oathes and covenants &amp;c. And whether thoſe that are Judges of others ſhould not doe better firſt to Judge themſelves.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer,</hi> 27.</head>
                     <p>Whether that clauſe of the Ordinance which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judgeth ſuch Miniſters to be ejected as have, or ſhall declare their diſaffection to the preſent Government without excepting any, no not thoſe that either have changed, or ſhall hereafter change their thoughts and affections into a better eſteem and liking of it, will not, in probability rather confirm thoſe that have been or ſhall be diſaffected in that their diſaffection for ever, then induce or perſwade any of them to approve of, or comply with that Government, being excluded from all favour or mercy if they doe, having been once guilty of diſaffection towards it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="query">
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:153957:21"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 29.</head>
                     <p>Whether the omitting of publick Catechiſing on the Lords day for many years together, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glecting to adminiſter the holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper for as many are not criſhes of an higher nature, and more meriting the ejection of thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, that are guilty of them, then the omitting for one Lords Day or two or ten, the publick praying or preaching on that day. Whenas publick Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing hath been acknowledged by our adverſaries to have been the prime way of inſtruction, wherein we of the Reformed Religion have ſo much out-ſtript them, and gotten ſo much ground of them. And the often celebrating of the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is our only way of commemorating Chriſt's death and paſſion, that Chriſt himſelf hath preſcribed us, and the prime means of ſealing and aſſuring to us all the benefit thereof, even whatſoever Chriſt hath in his Goſpel promiſed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 30.</head>
                     <p>Whether the act expreſſing how often omiſſion of publick praying and preaching upon the Lords Day, either in a year, or in a mans life time, ſhall be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch negligence as that the Miniſter guilty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhall be ejected, as alſo how long abſence from his cure, and at what diſtance, ſhall be accounted non Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence, Does not expoſe all Miniſters to ſtrange and inavoidable hazzards of looſing their Livings or cures, according as five ſeverall Commiſſioners, ſhall, at ſeverall times, upon ſeverall occaſions, in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall judgements alterable every day, pleaſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="query">
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:153957:21"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 31.</head>
                     <p>Whether it had not been requiſite and neceſſary, for the preventing of malice and revenge in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or parties accuſing, and for the preſerving of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and uprightneſs in the party accuſed, and for the avoiding of perjury and ſubornation of perjury in the Witneſſes on the behalf of both, as alſo for the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and juſtifying of the proceedings and determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the commiſſioners and the through ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their conſciences therein, That there ſhould have been ſome time limited and preſcribed for every accuſer of any Miniſter, concerning any of the crimes mentioned or referred to in the Ordinance to bring in his charge or accuſation into the open court of the Commiſſioners, and then to preſent it to them, which in ſo many dayes or weeks after any of thoſe crimes, whereof he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>uſeth him, were committed; or elſe that his charge or accuſation ſhould not be received or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted of any validity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 32.</head>
                     <p>Whether upon the rendering of Miniſters thus li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to whatſoever men and devils can in the height of malice and depth of conſpiracy contrive or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire againſt them. All ſober and diſcreet men will not avoid the bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ing up their children for that holy calling, which is of it ſelf ſo perilous to the moſt able and faithfull, and is now, by this Ordinance expoſed to ſo much ſcorn, and contempt, and perſecution by all the enemies thereof. And ſo the Miniſtery of England muſt needs be ſoon worne out that way and the people be left without any Shepherd or have only blind guides, and thoſe of the loweſt of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to go in and out before them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="33" type="query">
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:153957:22"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 33.</head>
                     <p>Whether, upon the ejection of ſo many Miniſters, as 'tis viſible will be ejected by this Ordinance, There will not be very many poor ſouls, even whole congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of them, in all parts of this Nation, ſuddenly left deſtitute of any Paſtor or Teacher to feed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them; or elſe one Paſtor or Teacher muſt be intereſted with a tot quot of cures, as ſome, not fit to officiate in any cure (witneſſe that there was vanity and iniquity of boaſting that they ſhould have ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) have already bragged that they ſhall ere long have five or ſix a piece. And beſides 'tis to be feared (or rather it cannot be avoided) That notorious He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques, cloſe Romaniſts, and mad Mechanicks will creep into cures of ſoules, as well as into pulpits in a multitude of Pariſhes, as they have done already in ſome, and ſo devour many poor ſouls for whom Chriſt ſhed his blood. For what ſhall keep ſuch out? when if they have but ſo much impudency and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, as to tell two or three holy lies of the ſame and manner of their converſion (though they never were ſo wicked then when they ſo belyed God and themſelves, by faigning themſelves to have been ſo converted from their wickedneſſe) and then whine or ſnivel three or four time-ſerving principles, and anſwer, or admire at, four or five ſtrange mungrel queſtions, which ſome of the propounders themſelves underſtood not, and thoſe that have any ingenuity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them can ſcarce forbear laughing at &amp; for the palliating their ignorance diſclaime human learning as ſavouring too much of the two univerſities Rome and Babylon; &amp; at the laſt, If theſe rare gifts take not with all the Examiners, be but furniſhed with one good gift
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:153957:22"/>or two more in their hands to open ſome of the others mouths to ſpeak a few good words in private on their behalf, and to ſay how they are affected and what opinion they are of, though their judgements never ſo ſmall or weak, (all which any Heretick, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſt, and illiterate mechanick may eaſily do) who ſhall dare to appear againſt them, unleſſe they did hazard the loſſe of their own Livings for the oppoſing ſuch that ſteal men in their ſtealing into other.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="34" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 34.</head>
                     <p>Whether the ejecting of ſo many Miniſters by this Ordinance, as are likely to be ejected, if the Ordinance it ſelf be not repealed by his Highneſſe with your Honours advice, will not bring a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſcandall upon the Reformed Proteſtant Religion here in this Nation (and that not without ſome reflection of diſhonour upon other Reformed Churches in other Nations) throughout Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome and elſewhere, then all thoſe Miniſters that ſhall be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected thereby, could ever have brought upon it, had they been all really guilty of all the ſcandalous crimes whereof they are or ſhall be maliciouſly and falſely accuſed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="35" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 35.</head>
                     <p>Whether it be not more then probable. That, as ſince the former ejecting, ſequeſtring or removing, that is, one word depriving (for all or the moſt cicetions, ſequeſtrations, or removes of Clergy-men, have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved utter deprivations) of ſo many Miniſters by the late Parliament, ſo many Atheiſticall, hereticall, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous and execrable opinions, derogatory to the honour of God and deſtructive to humane ſociety, have ſprung up amongſt us, and ſo many Popiſh points of doctrine have been maintained and propagated in all parts of this Nation, even by ſome that do pretend to abhorre the name of Popery, as well as by others. So likewiſe now, after that ſo many Miniſters more ſhall be ejected by this Ordinance, The number of the foreſaid horrid opinions and dangerous points of Doctrine will be very much augmented and increaſed
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:153957:23"/>in every Corner, nay in every open ſtreet, beſides ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other miſchiefs that will grow apace upon us, that are not yet ſo evidently diſcernable; and of which his Highneſſe himſelf, when it is too late, may be as ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible as any other? For they, who thus ſtrike at the Miniſtery, will be as ready and as adventurous upon the leaſt advantage they can find or make, to knock down the Magiſtracy.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="36" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 36.</head>
                     <p>Whether, all theſe things conſidered, unleſſe this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance be repealed, the ſtrange proceedings, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraleld ſentences of each ſuch Commiſſion-Court in every County, together with the many ſad effects and conſequents, that will undoubtedly follow thereupon, will not very much juſtifie all, even all the exprobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, illegalities, and cruelties, ſo much complained of and cried out againſt by the late Parliament, both in the High Commiſsion Court of each Province, and in all Eccleſiaſtical Courts in every Dioceſs: and what the ſenſe thereof may in time produce, let the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iſſues of thoſe former cries againſt thoſe Courts, warn all that may be concerned.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="37" type="query">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Quaer.</hi> 37.</head>
                     <p>Whether, in caſe this Ordinance (notwithſtanding all this) ſhould for the ſins and iniquites both of the Miniſters and People of this Nation be ſtill continued in force: (which the Lord of his mercy forbid, and rather take it into his own hands, then deliver us into the hands of ſuch men) or if any other Commiſſion ſhould be eſtabliſhed by any other Ordinance or Act (if the Lawes already eſtabliſhed have not provided ſufficient puniſhment for ſuch offenders) for the admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing, puniſhing, and (if neither of them will amend them) for the ejecting of ſcandalous, ignorant &amp; inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:153957:23"/>Miniſters &amp; Schoolmaſters which ought to be done, and we pray it may be done (if God ſee it fit and requiſite to be done,) with infinite caution, wiſedome prudence and impartiality, It be not then very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, That all the allegations, accuſations or charges of all and every of the accuſers and proſecutors of Miniſters, and all the Anſwers and pleas of the ſaid Miniſters in defence of themſelſes and their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, together with all the teſtimonies and depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of witneſſeſſes on both parts, As alſo all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, adjudications, or determinations of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners thereupon, with the grounds and reaſons thereof. Be exactly and punctually regiſtred and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, and all the particulars thereof, preceding ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence be openly and diſtinctly read in Court immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately before any ſentence or judgement be paſſed; that all the perſons in their ſeverall relations forenamed &amp; concerned therein, may hear, and be aſſured, whether each particular be, as he or they delivered and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it, or not: and if not, then to have liberty to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect or amend whatſoever he or they were miſtaken or miſunderſtood in. And then, when ſentence is ſo paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; That the ſaid Sentence it ſelf and the grounds thereof be alſo read in open Court, and the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners hands that paſſed it, ſet thereto. To the intent, that both the accuſers and proſecutors may be the more wary and juſt in their ſaid allegations, accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or charges, and the Accuſed the more watchfull and diſcreet in their anſwers and pleas, and the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes on both parts the more cautelous aed conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in their teſtimonies and depoſitions, and the Commiſſioners the more circumſpect and impartiall in their ſentences and determinations: as alſo, that all,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:153957:24"/>that deſire to be informed of the full truth of any, or all thoſe tranſactions, may be the better ſatiſfied; and which is not the leaſt, That his Highneſſe, in all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints or appeales of injuſtice or grievance, may the more eaſily and accurately judge thereof.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <p>Theſe Quaeries I have laid at your Honours feet, moſt humbly beſeeching you to take them up and to peruſe them, onely ſo long as till, upon thorow examination of them and conſultation about them, you ſhall find whither they may do you, and the diſtreſſed Church of God here in England, any ſervice or not in that great and weighty buſineſſe, which is reported to be taken into your care, Namely, the inquiring into the particulars of the Ordinance for the ejecting of Miniſters. And if not, that you would lay them there again, and trample on them, and on him that preſents them (if he can be more trampled on then he is) for diſturbing your more ſerious conſultations with ſuch fruitleſſe queſtions. But yet, if they can no other way ſerve you or advantage that pious work of yours in ſcarching into the dangerous clauſes and deſperate conſequents of that Miniſter deſtroying Ordinance, they may ſerve to ſhew my ſenſibleneſſe of the enemies of the true Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion's indeavours to bring us all to confuſion; as well as my deſire to do my utmoſt to prevent it; And (which I cannot ſmother) my real compaſſion and truely Sympathiſing affection to my poore perſecuted brethren of the Miniſtry: though too many of them (the Lord lay it not their charge) have ſhown little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion or affection to me and others of their Brethren when we were eiected, His Highneſſe who gave life to this ordinance, will not, I hope, think the worſe of me for my thus preſumptuous med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with it: when I profeſſe ſolnmely, that I cannot but in Charity believe, that although it had his fiat when it was contrived, yet it had nothing of his contrivement in it, more then that Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, ignorant, and inſufficent Miniſters and School-maſters ſhould be eiected: but ſurely, it was never his intention, that eiection ſhould be ſo far extended, and ſuch men impowred to execute it, as that the beſt of Miniſters, yea the whole Miniſtry of England ſhould be deſtroyed; or at leaſt made lyable ſo to be, when the enemies thereof ſhould find their long deſired opportunity. No this deſign certainly came from the Ignatian Conclave, and from
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:153957:24"/>the Convents of ſome Aritiminiſteriall Heretiques; the former aiming at the ruine of the Reformed Miniſtry of this Nation, the latter at the deſtruction of all Miniſters whatſoever. And ſuch a deſigne, eſpecially when it was covered over with thoſe ſpecious pretences of further Reformation and of the Goſpels propagation, might eaſily eſcape his Highneſſe diſcerning having ſuch a cloud of high concerning affairs incompaſſing him. But if his Highneſſe, who knows me well) ſhould take this ill from me, when I intend him not the leaſt ill by it; He knowes likewiſe, that, as I deſire not to diſpleaſe men by my ſpeaking, ſo I dare not much more diſpleaſe God by my ſilence. And therefore, when the glory of God and the ſafety of his Church is ſo nearly concerned, ſhould my tongue now cleave to my mouth, I ſhould feare, either the being ſtruck quite dumbe here, or the being made to open it in vain cries and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded complaints hereafter. And for your Honours, and all others of honour and honeſty, I have cauſe to believe you will the ſooner and the more attend to what I ſay, becauſe many of you know me to be wholly unconcerned and unintereſted, as to mine own parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, in any thing, that this Ordinance takes notice of or openly declares againſt. For the deſires of my ſoul are for a more effectual propagation of the Goſpel, and for the ſettlement of a more pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſtry: And (to the praiſe and glory of Gods grace be it wholly ſpoken) there are none, no not the worſt of mine enemies, that can charge me with any crime, or ought, that is indeed ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, or with any of thoſe things which this Ordinance adjudged to be ſcandalous, further then I am able to juſtify both my ſelf and them from giving any juſt occaſion to be ſo adjudged. And (which I am neither aſhamed nor affraid to acknowledge nor may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge without bleſſing God for his calling me and others to beare it patiently &amp; cheerfully) I am one of thoſe deſpiſed ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, that is, ejected Miniſters, that were long ſince caſt out of our Livings, not for any ſcandall, ignorance, or negligence, but (which is our glory and comfort) for diſcharging our Loyalty and fidelity to our then Soveraign, and for our love and conſtancy to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed doctrine and diſcipline of the Church of England, or, (which is their ſhame, I would I could add, ſorrow) for the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of ſome of our convetous, ambitious, malious Brethren's thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting after our poſſeſſions and lively-hoods. And therefore being neither guilty of any of thoſe living depriving crimes, nor having
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:153957:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>any living to feare the being deprived of, I may be heard the more freely and unſuſpectedly in what I plead for others, and thoſe too, many of them, ſuch, as never ſo much as opened their mouths in the behalf of me or any of my fellow-ſufferrers, either in pleading for us when we were to be ejected, or in commiſerating our diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed condition ſince, but either compl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yed with our enemies, or moved neither tongue nor pen againſt them. If I had been of their temper, or of ſome others judgement better then my ſelf, I might with much pretence of reaſon, and perhaps Religion, not only have forborn to appeare in this cauſe, but have thought it my duty rather to be ſilent, and to admire at Gods Juſtice in this ſignall progreſſe of his judgements, in bringing them now upon them, who, if they (did not too many of them) help to bring them upon others, were too ſilent &amp; inſenſible, when ſo many thouſands of us firſt groaned under them, and a multitude periſhed by them. But I have long ſince forgiven them and all others, ſo far as concernes my ſelf; and I beſeech the Lord to give them yet, if he have not already, ſuch ſenſe of, and ſorrow for, both that and all other their ſins, that they may receive comfort and aſſurance from him of the pardon of them ſo far as concernes all others, and to grant both to them and to us all, that are of the Miniſtry, ſo much grace, that we may ſpeedily and moſt ſtrictly ſearch and try our own hearts and wayes, and by that ſearch find what thoſe things are whereby we have provoked him to ſo much wrath and indignation againſt us, his erſt while highly honoured,<note place="margin">contemned</note> but now baſely continued Diſpenſers of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and upon our finding what thoſe things are, to direct and ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble us ſo to poure out our ſouls in the humble confeſſing &amp; unfeigned repenting of them, that we returning to him the Shepherd and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of our Souls, He may in mercy return to us the deſpiſed She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pherds and Biſhops of his Sheep and reſtore us to our wonted ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and eſteem again, (if it be his will) or howſoever to the liberty and happineſſe of exerciſing our function with freedome ſucceſſe, and comfort, to his Glory, to the benefit of his Church to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of our own ſouls, and to the converſion, or confuſion of his, his Churches and our otherwiſe implacable, Enemies. Amen, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
